Guide to the Samuel Loveman Correspondence
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Samuel Loveman Correspondence
1911-1976.
Loveman, Samuel, 1887-1976.
0.42 linear ft. ( 1 document box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0806
4079049
This collection contains correspondence sent to the New York bookseller, poet, and collector, Samuel Loveman.
Biographical Note
Samuel Loveman was born in 1887 in Cleveland, Ohio. An aspiring poet, Loveman left the Midwest in order to pursuer his career as a writer and to live an openly gay lifestyle. He moved to New York City in the early 1920s where he made the acquaintance of several prominent authors including Ambrose Bierce, Hart Crane, and H.P. Lovecraft. Loveman owned a bookstore named the Bodley Bookshop in Manhattan with his partner David Mann. He wrote two books, The Hermaphrodite was a poem published in July 1926 and subsequently republished with additional poems in 1936 and Twenty-One Letters, a collection of letters sent to him by Ambrose Bierce. He also published The Sphinx in 1944. Loveman died in relative obscurity at the Jewish Home and Hospital in 1976.
Scope and Content
The Samuel Loveman Correspondence collection contains letters primarily sent to Loveman by friends, colleagues, and admirers. Subjects written about include the legacy and growing interest in author Hart Crane and Loveman's connection to him, antiquarianism, and books. There is a small amount of letters complimenting Loveman on his poetry. Sculptor Ahron Ben-Shmuel is well represented in the collection with letters spanning several decades.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically.
Subjects
Ben-Shmuel, Aron, 1903-; Loveman, Samuel, 1887-1976; Literature.; Booksellers and bookselling.; Authors.; Scholars.; Antiquarian booksellers.; Poetry; Gay authors--New York (City); Poets.
- Correspondence
  - A, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B, undated, 1948-1958, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ben-Shmuel, Ahron, undated, 1940-1950, 1964-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C, 1931-1937, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - D, 1929, 1951-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - E through F, 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - G, 1943, 1952, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gautier-Roman, Rizal, undated, 1929-1932, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - H, undated, 1931, 1945-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - J through K, 1933, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - L, undated, 1940, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - M, 1927-1939, 1951- 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - O, 1934-1935, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - P through R, undated, 1952, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - S, undated, 1926-1934, 1963, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - T, 1912, 1932- 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - U through W, undated, 1927-1935, 1948- 1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified Individuals, undated, 1928, 1938 -1959, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)